YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 1. General and History
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records: Record Group 01. General and History
1877-2003
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
324_rg1
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This record group contains reference files compiled from the National Board Library collection and National Board Archives providing general historical information about the YWCA of the U.S.A., its organizational structure, requirements for membership, and affiliation with the World YWCA. Also included are biographical files on staff and board members and reference files on the World YWCA and national YWCAs in other countries. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm. Links to the lists for both formats are provided in the Series Descriptions.
This record group contains reference files compiled from the National Board Library collection and National Board Archives providing general historical information about the YWCA of the U.S.A., its organizational structure, requirements for membership, and affiliation with the World YWCA. Also included are biographical files on staff and board members and reference files on the World YWCA and national YWCAs in other countries. Historical notes for each series are not included in this record. Where applicable, the Series Descriptions refer researchers to relevant Historical notes in other sections.
This Record Group is divided into seven Series:
I. GENERAL
II. REORGANIZATIONS
III. MEMBERSHIP OF INDIVIDUALS
IV. ANNIVERSARIES
V. BIOGRAPHICAL FILES
VI. 'FOREIGN' YWCAS REFERENCE FILES
VII. WORLD YWCA REFERENCE FILES
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
Asia--Description and travel--Sources; China--Description and travel--Sources; China--History--1912-1949--Sources; World Young Women's Christian Association
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
Series Descriptions
- SERIES I. GENERAL
  This series includes basic historical information about the YWCA of the U.S.A., its constitution, purpose, organizational structure, and staff. The records consist of articles, fact sheets, theses, books, pamphlets, and manuscripts on the history of the YWCA of the U.S.A.; copies of the YWCA's charter, constitution and by-laws, and Purpose, with minutes, notes, and correspondence about various revisions; Annual Reports; general information about Committees, Councils, and Departments, including charters and rosters; organization charts; staff rosters and office/telephone directories.
  Microfilmed Records, 1884-1970 only
  [see Microfilmed Records Reel Lists]
  Many of the basic histories written by YWCA staff and members were among the last items filmed in Part 2c of the Subject Files and can be found under YWCA, History. Annual Reports and Constitution and By-laws up to 1970 are also available on the microfilm.
  General historical items can be found on the microfilm under:
  Predecessor Organizations, Minutes, and Reports
  By-laws of National Board YWCA
  By-laws and Constitution of the YWCA of the U.S.A.
  Subject Files
  National Board, Reports [Annual Reports]
  YWCA, Constitution
  YWCA, Handbook
  YWCA, Historical Summaries
  YWCA, Purpose
  YWCA, Yearbook
  Original Format Records, 1889-2000, n.d., 5 linear ft.
  [see Original Format Records folder list]
  Most of the Microfilmed Records are also available in Original Format. In addition to the post-1970 records on Constitution amendments, updates of the Purpose, and Annual Reports, there is also some more recent historical writing about the YWCA. The Original Format files of organization charts and staff rosters/telephone directories are much more comprehensive than what is available on the microfilm.
  Related Materials
  Discussions of all changes to the Constitution and Purpose of the YWCA can be found in RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONFERENCES AND CONVENTIONS.
  Videotaped panels and presentations related to the YWCA's reexamination of its Purpose in the late 1980s and its mission as a Single sex organization in the late 1980s-early 1990s are in RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIO-VISUAL MATERIALS
- SERIES II. REORGANIZATIONS
  Historical information about the major administrative reorganizations can be found in the general Historical Note and in the Historical Notes for RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM, and RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS.
  This series contains the major studies of the National Association administrative structure done by outside consultants and National Association Committees. Generally, reorganizations were prompted by financial crises and the Association more often than not opted to implement some of the concepts, but did not adopt the recommendations wholesale. In some cases, as in the Organizational Renewal plan of the early 1970s, financial constraints prevented full application of the plan. In addition to the studies there are minutes, reports, and working files of committees and commissions.
  The bulk of the records are related to the series of "redesign" and "strategic planning" efforts begun in the late 1980s that ultimately led to the major restructuring of the National Association in 1999-2000. Included are many notes, reports, memoranda, surveys, and other materials from the Governance Task Force (1988-92); Project Redesign (1992-93); Strategic Planning Initiative (1994-2000), and Change Initiative (1998-2000).
  Microfilmed Records, 1906-70 only
  Records about YWCA reorganizations can be found on the microfilm under:
  General Administration
  National Board, Reorganization
  National Board, Survey
  YWCA, Study
  Original Format Records, 1921-2001, 3.5 linear ft.
  [see Original Format Records Folder List]
  Most of the pre-1971 Original Format Records can also be found on the Microfilm. The later files, provide extensive documentation of the Association's internal struggles in the final two decades of the 20th Century. The records are arranged chronologically.
  A number of meetings, discussions, and presentations related to the 1980s-2000 reorganizations were videotaped. The videotapes are in RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
- SERIES III. MEMBERSHIP OF INDIVIDUALS
  Historical information about requirements for membership of individuals can be found in the general Historical Note and in the Historical Notes for RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM (especially under Religion), and RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS.
  This series contains general and historical materials; files on policies and practices related to individuals (as opposed to Community or Student Association's membership in the National Association); and publications and committee records related to the recruitment and development of new members.
  Included are records of the Basis Commission, 1913-19, charged with examining the requirement that YWCA members must be members of Evangelical Protestant churches; and the Corresponding Membership system, 1920-31, which allowed women who lived in regions of the country where there was no YWCA to join the National Association directly (as opposed to being members in the National by virtue of their membership in a Community or Student Association.) Records of post-World War II membership committees are more likely to be concerned with definition of terms such as member, elector, and participant; fee structures; and the status of men and boys in YWCA programs. From the 1960s on, Association committees expended increasing energy on recruitment of new members.
  Microfilmed records include the records of the main pre-1971 committees involved with individual membership. Records of the Basis Commission are in the Subject Files under YWCA, Membership, rather than in the Minutes and Reports.
  Records about membership of individuals can be found on the microfilm under:
  Minutes and Reports
  Corresponding Membership Committee
  Membership Policies Committee
  YWCA, Membership
  YWCA, Policies and Standards
  Original Format Records, 1913-93, n.d., 1.5 linear ft.
  The Original Format Records are arranged in three sections: General and History; Policies and Practices; and Recruitment and Development. General and History consists of two theses written in 1951 and 1954 on membership in the YWCA. Policies and Practices includes forms, committee records, reports, studies, and publications. Recruitment and Development contains committee records, publications, and records of the late 1980s "Why Double You?" membership campaign. Most of the Original Format Records pre-1971 are also on the microfilm.
  Extensive discussions of issues related to individuals' requirements for membership can be found in the records of the two predecessor organizations in RECORD GROUP 2 and in Convention records in RECORD GROUP 4.
- SERIES IV. ANNIVERSARIES
  Over the 20th century, the YWCA chose to mark different anniversaries in its history, including:
  1855 founding of two organizations in Great Britain which later merged and took the name Young Women's Christian Association
  1858 founding of the Ladies Christian Union of New York (now considered the first YWCA in the U.S.)
  1866 founding of the Boston YWCA (originally thought to be the first YWCA in the U.S.)
  1894 founding of the international organization called World YWCA
  1906-07 founding of the YWCA of the U.S.A. (The first joint Convention of the two predecessor organizations was in 1906; the Association was incorporated in 1907)
  1912 dedication of the YWCA of the U.S.A. headquarters building at 600 Lexington Ave., New York City
  The Anniversaries records consist of minutes, planning materials, programs and other publications, and publicity from various YWCA anniversaries, 1916-94.
  Documentation is especially rich for the "World YWCA Centennial" in 1955 (the centennial of the founding of the first proto-YWCAs in Great Britain-as opposed to the centennial of the organization, World YWCA) and the 135th Anniversary of the founding of the earliest U.S. Association in 1993-94. Included are extensive files on the traveling exhibit from 1993-94 "Women First for 135 Years."
  [see Microfilmed Records Reel list]
  The Microfilmed Records contain minutes, publications, and other records of the Jubilee in 1916, and a few fundraising and publicity materials from the 20th (1926) and 25th (1932) anniversaries. There are extensive records from the 1955 Centennial including planning materials, publications, minutes, committee records, fundraising, and publicity.
  Records about various anniversary celebrations can be found on the microfilm under:
  National Jubilee Committee
  Anniversaries
  Anniversary, Centennial (1955)
  Original Format Records, 1916-94, 2 linear ft.
  Original format records duplicate in large part what is on the microfilm, but also have modest amounts of information about anniversaries celebrated in 1937, and 1944. There are extensive 135th Anniversary files which post-date the microfilm and a small amount of material related to the centennial of the founding of the organization called the World YWCA in 1994. The records are arranged in chronological order.
  There are many photographs of 1955 "Centennial" and 1993-94 135th Anniversary events along with a few photographs of other anniversaries in RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS.
  Video presentations and television coverage of 125th and 135th Anniversary events can be found in RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
- SERIES V. BIOGRAPHICAL FILES
  The Biographical Files consist of a wide variety of materials compiled by the YWCA of the U.S.A. archives to provide easy access to basic information about YWCA staff (both national and in Community Associations) and National Board members and officers. There are also some materials on World YWCA officers and staff.
  The Biographical Files contain newspaper clippings, press releases, correspondence, speeches, essays, pamphlets, "Who's Who" biography forms, obituaries and memorials, awards and commendations, published biographies, family histories, YWCA personnel record cards, and publications authored by the subject of the file.
  General biographical files on some staff and National Board members can be found on the microfilm under:
  National Board, Deceased Board and Staff Members
  National Board, Members
  Original Format Records, 1906-2000, 9.5 linear ft.
  [see Original Format Records Folder list]
  The National Board Archives staff compiled files from a variety of sources, they include some of the people and items in the microfilmed files, but cover a wider date span and may include small amounts of personal correspondence and memorabilia donated to the YWCA Archives. Most of the National Association's personnel files were discarded, but small amounts of surviving materials, such as personnel record cards and questionnaires, were incorporated into these Biographical Files by National Board Archives staff.
- SERIES VI. 'FOREIGN' YWCAS REFERENCE FILES
  Historical information about the YWCA of the U.S.A.'s work with staff of the YWCA in other countries can be found in the Historical Note for RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK.
  With the exception of the records related to the YWCA of China, the historical files on "Foreign" YWCAs are small subject files consisting primarily of publications. In some cases there are scrapbooks or photograph albums, usually presented to the YWCA of the U.S.A. or to one of its "Foreign" staff as part of a ceremonial occasion. They are arranged alphabetically by country.
  The National Association's involvement with the YWCA of China dates back to the earliest days of the Association and included an unusually large number of American secretaries. Because of this, the files related to the YWCA of China are especially rich. In addition to brochures, reports, copies of minutes of the National Committee of the YWCA of China, financial records, and publications, there are a number of photograph albums donated to the YWCA Archives by American secretaries who served in China in the 1910s and 1920s.
  Microfilmed Records, 1877-1970 only
  [see Microfilmed Records Reel List]
  The Microfilmed Records have fairly extensive "reference" materials as part of the "Foreign" and "International" sections. Unfortunately, reels 51 and 52 (China, American Staff, Correspondence and Reports, Brennecke - China, Property, Canton) were lost some years ago before transfer to the Sophia Smith Collection.
  Reference files on YWCAs in other countries can be found on the microfilm under:
  Foreign
  Foreign Countries
  International
  Original Format Records, 1884-98, n.d., 5 linear feet
  The Original Format Records are arranged alphabetically by country. Due to the large size and scope of the YWCA of China materials, they are filed separately at the end of the series. Other larger files include those on the YWCA of Great Britain and the YWCA of India, Burma, and Ceylon, which contain copies of various serials put out by those Associations.
  Early materials on the "Foreign" work of the Predecessor Organization, the American Committee can be found in RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD.
  Records of the YWCA of the USA's International Work are in RECORD GROUP 5.
  The Sophia Smith Collection Periodicals Collection contains Today: Magazine of the YWCA of India for 1963-1979.
- SERIES VII. WORLD YWCA REFERENCE FILES
  This series is a general reference file on the umbrella international association to which the YWCA of the U.S.A. is affiliated, the World YWCA. It includes historical publications, general pamphlets, constitution, annual reports, publications, and files on conferences and councils, programmes and projects.
  The Microfilmed Records include general "reference" materials about the World YWCA along with records of the YWCA of the USA's interactions with the World YWCA. These can be found on the microfilm under:
  Foreign, World's YWCA
  Foreign, World YWCA
  Original Format Records, 1896-2003, n.d., 5.5 linear ft.
  Many of the "reference" materials on the Microfilm are also available in Original Format. The National Board Library and Archives also collected copies of a number of World YWCA publications, including Conference, Consultation, and Council proceedings and reports; and brochures and reports of Programmes and Projects.
  Records of YWCA of the USA correspondence with and participation in the World YWCA are in RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE.
  There is a also small amount of related material in RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK.
  RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS contains videotaped "reviews" of various World Council Meetings dating from the mid-1980s, plus extensive footage of the 1987 World Council meetings which were held in the U.S.
- SERIES I. GENERAL
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Series Descriptions for historical and scope and content notes.
  - Miscellaneous historical materials, 1906-2000, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - YWCA History Fact Sheets
    - General, 1971-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Employed Women, 1953-80 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Firsts, 1983-94 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Predecessor organizations, 1889-1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Student, 1972-73, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Articles, manuscripts, theses, books, pamphlets
    - The Development of the Young People's Movement by Frank Otis Erb, University of Chicago Press, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fifty Years of Association Work Among Women, 1866-1916: A History of the Young Women's Christian Associations of the United States of America by Elizabeth Wilson, National Board, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The First Twenty-Five Years: Being a Summary of the Work of the Young Women's Christian Associations of the United States of America, 1906-1931 by Mary S. Sims, The Womans Press, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - From Deep Roots: The Story of the YWCA's Religious Dimensions by Frances Helen Mains and Grace Loucks Elliott, National Board, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The Girl Reserve Movement of the Young Women's Christian Association: An Analysis of the Educational Principles and Procedures Used Throughout Its History by Catherine S. Vance, Teachers College, Columbia University, Contributions to Education, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - The Growth and Development of the Young Women's Christian Association: An Interpretation by Elizabeth Russell Hendee, The Womans Press, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Historical Outline of the Young Women's Christian Association Movement in America, National Board, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Historical Papers" (or "Jubilee Sketches"), 1916 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - A History of the World's Young Women's Christian Association by Anna V. Rice, The Woman's Press, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The National and International Work of the YWCA, Finance and Publicity Department, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - The Natural History of a Social Institution-The Young Women's Christian Association by Mary S. Sims
      - Published version, Womans Press, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Thesis, New York University, 1935
        - Part 1 (Box 2)
        - Parts 2-4 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - The Past is Prelude: Fifty Years of Social Action in the YWCA "prepared" by Elsie D. Harper, Bureau of Communications, National Board, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Purpose Widens, 1947-67 by Mary S. Sims, National Board, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - The Religious and Educational Philosophy of the Young Women's Christian Association: A historical study of the changing religious and social emphases of the Association as they relate to changes in its educational philosophy and to observable trends in current religious thought, educational philosophy, and social situations by Grace H. Wilson, Bureau of Publications, Teachers College, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - See What You've Got Into! Introducing the YWCA to New Members by Margaret Hiller, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Women, Reform, and Feminism: the Young Women's Christian Association and the American Friends Service Committee, 1945-1960" by Susan Lynn, PhD thesis: Stanford University, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8-11)
    - "Women's leadership within the YWCA: after implementation of Steps to Absolute Change" by Avery L. Slyker, Ph.D. thesis, Capella University, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "The Young Women's Christian Association: An American and World Organization," unsigned typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A., National Board of the (YWCA-USA) by Ann Nicholl in Social Service Organizations, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "The YWCA Then and Now," by Odile Sweeney: text, correspondence, and notes, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - The Young Women's Christian Association-What Is It? by Inez Ensign, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - The YWCA: An Unfolding Purpose by Mary S. Sims, Woman's Press, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Pictorial historical publications
    - Photo Memories of '600,' Communications Unit, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Pictorially Yours, YWCA, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Story of the YWCA by Helen Southard, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Wherever She Is…, [1960] (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Awards and commendations, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Calendars of national YWCA events, 1993-2001 (Box 4, Folder 10a)
  - Charter, Constitution, and By-laws
    - Act of Incorporation/Charter
      - 1907 and amended, 1934, 1936, 1941, 1945, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence re amendments to charter, 1925-50 (Box 4, Folder 12-15)
    - Corporation Seal, 1923-50, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Official name of Association, 1989-95 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Constitution and By-laws
      - Constitutions under which conventions functioned, 1906-36 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Constitution, 1915-40 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - By-laws
        - 1917-26 (Box 4, Folder 20)
        - 1941-98 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
      - Constitution and By-laws, 1949-98 (Box 5, Folder 4-6)
      - Committees